露西...
Lucy...
你好 亲爱的!
Hello,darling!
主是我的守护者 我不应该害怕
The Lord is my Sheperd,and I shall not fear.
在天堂他指引着我
In green pastures He leads me,
在静水边上...
beside still waters...
大侦探波罗探案集
第9季第1集
啤酒谋杀案
谢谢
Merci.
- 干杯 - 干杯
- Sante. - Sante.
那么
Alors
- 莱马钱特小姐 - 首先 波罗先生
- Mademoiselle Lemarchant... - For starters,Monsieur Poirot,
这不是我的名字
that is not my name.
什么 我认为我是和莱马钱特小姐
Pardon,but I understood it was with Mademoiselle Lemarchant
见面的 - 这是我小时候的名字
that I was to meet. - That was the name I was given as a child.
我真名叫露西 露西・克雷尔
My real name is Crale,Lucy Crale.
克雷尔! 好吧 我似乎记得...
Crale! Now,I seem to remember...
我的父亲是艾米亚斯・克雷尔
My father was Amyas Crale,
艺术家 我的母亲是
the artist,and my mother was...
- 凯若琳 - 凯若琳・克雷尔
- Caroline. - Caroline... Crale.
- 是的 - 是的 是的...
- That's right. - Yes,yes...
这故事很悲剧
A story most tragic.
- 但过去很久了 对吗? - 十四年了
- But it was a long time ago,yes? - Fourteen years.
十四年?
14 years?
知道吗 我看过一副你父亲在塔特...
You know,I saw a picture that your father painted...
画过的画
... in the Tate.
"阴影中的女孩"
"Girl In The Shadow" .
"阴影中的女孩" 就是这个
"Girl In The Shadow" . That was the one.
它是广被追捧的作品
It is a composition most tracking.
是的 他是很了不起的画家
Yes,he was a great painter.
他的名声确实很大
His reputation is,yes,considerable.
我不是来这谈论他的艺术造诣的
I'm not here to discuss his art,Mr Poirot.
我来是希望您调查他的谋杀案
I'm here because I want you to investigate his murder.
我当时才七岁 年纪太小 什么都不知道
I was 7 at the time. Too young,really,to know anything about it.
我们住在德文郡一间叫阿德博瑞的宅子里
We lived in Devon,in a house called Alderbury.
我父母亲十分相爱
My parents were very much in love and,in many ways,
对我而言是田园诗般的童年
it was an idyllic childhood.
但有一天 我突然被带走
But then,one day,I was suddenly taken from my home
并被送到在加拿大的亲戚家
and sent to relatives,in Canada.
直到现在我21岁了 他们才告诉我真相
Then finally,when I turned 21,they were obliged to tell me the truth.
一方面 我是回来继承遗产的
For one thing,I came into my own money.
另一方面 你也看到了 这儿有封信...
And then,you see,there's the letter...
- 信? - 我母亲临死前
- The letter? - That my mother wrote me
写给我的信
just before she died.
我这才知道我母亲是因为谋杀亲夫被绞死的
That was the first I knew that my mother was hanged for killing my father.
- 她写了什么? - 就是说她没有杀人
- What did she write? - Quite simply that she didn't do it.
她是无辜的 我很确定这一点
She is innocent,and I could always be sure of that.
这就是我想你证明的
That is what I want you to prove.
但为什么是赫尔克里・波罗呢 小姐?
But why Hercule Poirot,Mademoiselle?
我听说过你和你的事迹
I've heard about you,the things you've done,
你工作的方式
the way you work.
心理学是你的"特长" 对吗?
The psycology is your "forte",n'est-ce pas?
是的 确实是 我确实在心理学
Oui,c'est vrai. My success
小有成就 或者说...
it is found in psycology,or...
... 人们"为什么"做出这样的行为
... the " why" of human behavior.
我用的是这里
It is this that I use.
但是 女士 这事过去太久了
Tout de mme,Mademoiselle,it is so long since it happened.
只是秘密与谎言 先生
Secrets and lies,Monsieur.
回忆不断纠缠着我 这些鬼魂不会放过我
The past keeps pulling me back,it won't let me be.
除非他们得到安息
And until these ghosts are laid to rest,
我无法继续我的生活
I can't move on.
好的
Bon,
对你的信任我感到荣幸
I am honored by your faith in me.
但是...
But...
我不能接受你确信你母亲是无辜的的
I can not,you understand,accept the insurance about the innocence of your mother.
如果她确实有罪呢 怎么办?
And if she was guillty,what then?
我必须知道真相 先生
I have to know the truth,Monsieur.
如果真相并不是你所期许的呢?
And if the truth is not what you wish to hear?
那我也要知道
I have to know.
... 带到死刑现场
... taken for a place of execution,
你会在那里被绞死
where you'll be hanged by the neck,until death.
我必须说 这不是我最成功的案例
Not one of my greatest successes,I have to say.
辩护说是自杀 对吗?
The defence was suicide,yes?
恐怕这说法说不通
Didn't get on too well,I'm affraid.
艾米亚斯・克雷尔不是会自杀的人
Amyas Crale simply wasn't that kind of chap.
酒 女人 啤酒...淫欲
Wine,women,beer... the lusts of the flesh.
良心发现而自杀...
The idea of his killing himself out of conscience...
好吧 老实说 我认为他没有良心
Well,frankly,I don't think he had one.
所以 你认为 蒙塔古先生
So,in your opinion,Sir Montague,
凯若琳・克雷尔是有罪的?
Caroline Crale,she was guilty?
我更相信我们认为这是理所当然
I rather thought that we were taking that for granted.
她认罪了吗?
Did she ever admit as much?
波罗先生 她不需要认罪
Monsieur Poirot,she didn't need to.
她一走进法庭 我就知道我们败诉了
I knew we had lost as soon as she stepped into this box.
她有动机
She certainly had a motive.
艾米亚斯・克雷尔总和身边的女人搞在一起
Amyas Crale was always mixed up with some woman around him,
但这个女人很不同
but this was rather different.
一个叫埃尔莎・格里尔的女孩 只有18岁
A girl. Elsa Greer. Just turned 18.
够漂亮 我只能说 她知道自己要的是什么
Quite a looker,I might say. She knew what she wanted,
那就是艾米亚斯・克雷尔 她让他给她画画
and that was Amyas Crale. She got him to paint her
最后他便爱上了她
he ended up falling for her.
有人听到凯若琳・克雷尔说...
Caroline Crale was overheard to say this...
... 如果他不离开她 她会杀了他
... if he didn't give her up,she'd kill him.
指控她的证据是什么?
What was the evidence against her?
她偷了邻居研究草药的毒药
She stole some poison from the neighbor who dabbled in herbs and alike,
藏在香水瓶里 后来警察在她房间里找到了
and hid it in a scent bottle,and when the police found it
她声称是她用来自杀的
in her room,she claimed she intended to kill herself.
但她不能解释为什么瓶子是空的
What she couldn't explain was why the bottle was empty
瓶子上只有她的指纹
and only her fingerprints were on it.
我们反驳说
We contempted,of course,
有可能是艾米亚斯・克雷尔用来自杀的
that Amyas Crale had used it to kill himself,
但是 如果是这样
but,if he had,
那瓶子上也应该有他的指纹
his fingerprints would be on it as well.
那她是怎么下毒的?
And how did she give it to him,this poison?
她用滴管把毒液注射入他的酒中
She used a pipet to spike his beer.
什么 先生 "注射?
Pardon,Monsieur. "Spike"?
额 混合 他画画的时候 她给了他一杯酒
Uh,tempered. She took him a bottle while he was painting.
警察在案发现场附近找到了破碎的滴管
The police found the pipet crashed near the scene of the crime.
起诉花了整整一天
The prosecution had a filled day.
这么说
So,
她在把酒给他之前已经下毒了?
she put the conium into the bottle before taking it to him?
不是的 杯子里没有毒药 只有酒杯上才有
No,there was no conium in the bottle at all,only in the glass.
我懂了!
I see!
还有什么你不解的吗?
Was that you beeing inscrutable,Mr Poirot?
没有了 没有了
Non,non. Pardon.
我想 当时应该还有人在现场吧?
But were there,I'd believe,other people present,at the time?
哦 是的 确实有 让我想想
Oh,yes,there were. Let me think.
我记得没错的话 有五个
Five,if memory serves.
菲利浦・布莱克 股票经纪人
Philip Blake,a stock broker,
是克雷尔最好的朋友之一
one of Crale's best friends;
梅雷迪斯 他的哥哥
Meredith,his older brother.
他住在河对面 正对案发的屋子
He lives across the estuary,from the house where the murder took place ;
埃尔莎・格里尔 当然
Elsa Greer,of course,
现在是迪蒂斯汉姆女士
currently Lady Dittisham,
尽管现在她的大多数时间花在
though now she spends most of her time
离婚法庭报的漫谈专栏上
in the gossip columns in the divorce Courts;
还有女家庭教师 ...
and the governess,Miss...
威尔逊小姐? 威廉斯! 就是这个!
Wilson? Williams! That's it!
很能干 但很少笑
Very capable,but not exactly a bottle of laughs.
当然 还有安吉拉 凯若琳同父异母的妹妹
Then,of course,there was Angela,Caroline's half-sister.
哦 在审判时她已经回到学校了 真可怜
Oh,she'd been off back to school,by the time of the trial. Poor thing.
- 她有问题吗? - 当她刚会走路时
- She had perhaps a problem? - There was a rather unfortunate incident,
发生了一件很不幸的事
when she was a toddler.
凯若琳・克雷尔 作为个年轻女孩
Caroline Crale,as a young girl,
发了通脾气
threw a bit of a tantrum.
我并不是说她不正常 但...
I did argue that she was not in her sain mind,but...
迷人的家伙! 我永远不会忘记她的
Fascinanting creature! I'll never forget her,you know?
她能让人情不自禁地喜欢她
She had a quality one couldn't help but admire.
不管怎么说 她就是这样
Somehow,she was,above it all.
以"爱"为名 人们会做出什么呢!
What people would do,in the name of love!
它使我们变成傻子 不是吗?
It makes fools of us all,n'est-ce pas?
好吧 谢谢你 蒙塔古先生 你的消息很有用
Eh bien,I thank you,Sir Montague. You have been most helpful.
很高兴见到你 波罗
Pleasure meeting you,Poirot.
请告诉我...
Tell to me,if you please...
如果 像她女儿所希望的那样
If,as her daughter hopes,
凯若琳・克雷尔没有杀她的丈夫...
Caroline Crale did not kill her husband...
可她杀了 伙计 记住我的话
But she did,old boy. Take my word for it.
...但是从逻辑上来说
... but then it makes the logic
这五个人也是有嫌疑的
that one of these 5 people must have done it.
他们没有理由这样做
There's no reason why any of them should.
是的 但是我还是会一一拜访他们
No,but all the same,I think I shall pay each of them a visit.
然后听到对这事的五种描述版本?
And hear five different versions of the same event?
谢谢 霍灵赫斯特
Thank you,Hollinghurst.
我的荣幸 布莱克先生
A pleasure,mr. Blake.
确实帮了大忙 老霍灵赫斯特
A fairly good aid,old Hollinghurst,
尽管对对手来说 他坏了大事
even though he does bat for the other side.
干杯!
Telly-o!
干杯...
Telly-o...
哇 没想到会和著名的赫尔克里・博罗举杯
Well,who'd have thought it? Raising a glass with the famous Hercule Porrow.
波罗 先生 赫尔克里・波罗
Poirot,Monsieur. Hercule Poirot.
波罗 博罗... 我永远发不好法语的音
Poirot,Porrow... Could never get my tongue around French.
我们相互谅解一下吧 嗯?
Let's keep the old  entente cordiale,eh?
但我是比利时人 先生 不是法国人
But I am Belgium,Monsieur,not French.
那么 我能为你做些什么?
So,what can I do for you?
是克雷尔的案子 先生 我想跟你讨论下这个
It is the Crale case,Monsieur. It is that which I wish to discuss with you.
究竟他妈的为了什么?
What the hell for?
因为我接受了重新调查这个案子的任务 先生
Because I have accepted the commission Monsieur to review the case.
- 谁是雇主? - 露西・克雷尔
- From whom? - Lucy Crale.
- 露西・克雷尔?- 是的 先生
- Lucy Crale? - Oui,Monsieur.
没什么好讨论的
Nothing to discuss.
只要五分钟 布莱克先生 我只需要五分钟
Five minutes of your time,Mr Blake,it is all that I ask.
她现在到底想打探些什么?
What the hell is she poking her nose in,now?
因为她想知道真相
Because she wishes to know  the truth.
每个人都知道真相!
Everyone knows the truth!
她只是想自己调查真相
But all she wishes is to access for herself the facts.
事情已经结束了 死了 埋了
It's over! Dead,buried.
她的父母也是这样 先生
As are her parents,Monsieur.
艾米亚斯・克雷尔是一个非常好的朋友
Amyas Crale was the best friend a chap could have.
我们小时候就认识了
We knew each other since we're children.
我们大家 我 我哥哥 凯若琳
We all,myself,my brother,Caroline.
是邻居 在德文郡的海边
Neighbors,you see. By the seaside,in Devon.
艾米亚斯是个玩咖 所有的天赋...
Amyas was a great play. And all that talent,that...
...生活的欲望 因为她 都收敛了
... lust for life,wiped out because of her.
你不喜欢她?
You did not like her?
完完全全的堕落了 艾米亚斯却不知道
Rotten... through and through. Amyas could never see it.
他原本就是个堕落的人 不是么?
But he was also something of a rotten,was he not?
她就是想让你们这么认为
That's what she'd have you believe.
噢 她喜欢装无辜 而且做得非常好
Oh,she liked playing the injured part,and did it very well,
但是...她的内心非常冷漠并且精于算计
but.... underneath it all,she was cold and calculating.
有魔鬼一样的坏脾气!
Had a devil of a temper!
她想杀他妹妹 天啊!
Tried to kill her baby sister,for God's sake!
- 真的假的? - 真的!
- Is it true? - Damn right.
她把镇纸扔向她 导致她的一只眼睛瞎了
Chucked a paperweight at her and blinded the little blight in one eye.
一生都毁了
Disfigured for life.
你知道她发脾气的原因么?
Do you know the reason for this fit of temper?
姐妹间的嫉妒 就这么简单
Sibling's jealousy,simple as that.
嫉妒让她杀了艾米亚斯
And were jealously that made her kill Amyas.
告诉你 那个女人是祸害
I tell you,that woman was trouble.
甚至当她是女孩的时候...
Even as a girl...
她玩弄我们男孩子的方式
the way she played us boys along.
让我们得出了同样的结论
Gave us all the one say,
最后她盯住了艾米亚斯
but finally settled on Amyas.
这并不奇怪
Not surprisingly.
他等着继承阿德博瑞 展现出了艺术家的天赋
He was in line to inherit Alderbury and showing talent as an artist.
一个真的天才 还有比这更好的吗?
A rich genius,what could be better?
很令人震惊 不是么
It is surprising,is it not,
生命的骰子多久才会掷一次?
how soon in life the dice is cast?
我想是的
Yes,I suppose it is.
无论如何 自从他们结了婚
Anyway,after the marriage,
我就一直跟他们保持距离
I kept my distance,
至少持续了一段时间 但是很快我又被诱惑
for a while,at least. But I soon succumbed to temptation.
诱惑 先生?
Temptation,Monsieur?
阿德博瑞
Alderbury.
一个我无法抗拒的地方
A place I couldn't resist.
在那我度过了人生中最快乐的时光
I spent some of the happiest times of my life in that house.
那个九月 就像童年时的夏天
That September,like the Summers of childhood,
我期待能平静的生活几个礼拜
I was hoping for a peaceful few weeks.
菲利浦叔叔!
Uncle Phil!
但我应该好好了解一下的
But I should've known better.
早上好 布莱克先生
Good morning,mr. Blake.
早上好 斯普里格斯女士
Good morning,Mrs. Spriggs.
- 很高兴又见到你 - 很高兴见到你
- It's good to see you again. - Good to see you.
艾米亚斯 拜托!
Amyas,please!
他们已经吵了几个小时了
They've been at it for hours.
- 你好 菲利浦叔叔 - 你好!
- Hello,uncle Phil. - Hello!
哦 长这么大了! 安吉拉在照顾你 是吧?
My,you grown! Angela's looking after you,is she?
- 不是? 不是? - 来吧 露西!
- No? No? - Com'on,Lucy!
- 来抓我啊! - 给她一次机会
- Catch me if you can! - Give her a chance.
等等我 安吉拉
Wait for me,Angela.
你为什么不听我的 艾米亚斯?
Why won't you listen to me,Amyas?
凯若琳 老天!
Caroline,for God's sake!
就是这样 像以前一想逃避
That's right,run away like ya always do.
花瓶摔了
There goes the jardinere.
空气中好像有点什么...
There was something up in the atmosphere...
但这一次 你可以用刀把它剪断
But this time,you could cut it with a knife.
很快我了解了原因
And I soon saw why.
艾米亚斯 好兄弟! 你怎么样?
Amyas,old chap! How the hell are ya?
她很可爱 对吧?
Lovely,isn't she?
有时我真希望不曾遇见她
Sometimes I wish I'd never met her.
感谢上帝你来了
Thank God you turned up.
和一屋子女人住在一起 当然想不起好兄弟了
Living in a house full of women is enough to send any men out to his chump.
菲利浦 见到你真高兴!
Philip,how lovely to see you!
你好 凯若琳
Hello,Caroline.
该吃午饭了 埃尔希也要一起吃吗?
Just in time for lunch. Will Elsie be joining us?
- 是埃尔莎 - 艾米亚斯在给她画画
- Elsa. - Amyas is doing her portrait.
活泼的妮子 她应该一直晒太阳 你知道吗?
Skittish little thing. She should watch all that sun,you know?
会老得很快的
Can be very ageing.
现在事情有点棘手啊
Things are a bit rocky at the moment.
真的吗 你和埃尔莎?
Is it serious,Elsa and you?
- 它会是一副很美的画 - 我不是问这个
- It'll be a damn good painting. - That's not what I asked.
你知道我的 菲利浦 我不能控制我自己
You know me,Phil. I can't help myself.
然后情况变得越来越糟
Then things got worse.
艾米亚斯和凯若琳的同父异母的妹妹安吉拉
Amyas and Caroline's half sister,Angela,
整个早上一直在搞闹矛盾
had been beckoning all morning.
你可以停下来吗 安吉拉?
Would you stop that please,Angela?
- 什么? - 吃得那么大声
- What? - Slurping.
- 我没发出声音 - 不 你有
- I'm not slurping. - Yes,you are.
艾米亚斯...
Amyas...
我觉得我该试试那件和服 金丝雀黄的那件
I thought I might try that other kimono,the canary yellow.
你不觉得在水边那颜色太闪了吗?
It could be rather stunning against that water,don't you think?
金丝雀! 多可爱啊
Canary! How lovely.
当然 有些人穿上会...
Of course on some people it might look a little...
我穿上会怎么样呢?
how shall I put it?
别担心 凯若琳 我很年轻能穿得出来
Don't worry,Caroline. I'm young enough to carry it on.
我们并没有要改变什么
We're not changing anything.
天啊! 你没听到吗?
For God...! Did you hear that?
就像猴子吃东西一样!
Looks like the feeding hour in the monkey house!
你就不能不管我吗?!
Why don't you just leave me alone?!
我从未见过这个
I hadn't seen this before.
这是沃格穆特・达尔的作品
It's by Wolgemut Dahl,
年轻的挪威画家 很出色 你觉得呢?
a young Norwegian. Extraordinary,don't you think?
每个人都在谈论他
Everyone's talking about him.
我会说 他很幽默
Got a sense of humor,I'll give him that.
你同意吗 威廉斯小姐?
Don't you agree,Miss Williams?
榉木 不是吗?
Beech wood,isn't it?
谢谢 斯普里格斯太太
Thank you,mrs. Spriggs.
如果房间里气氛没这么紧张就太好了
This room would be so lovely if it weren't so clutched.
等我住在这里 我要扔掉所有垃圾
When I'm living here,I'll throw out all the rubbish,
实话说 就是所有东西
which is,let's face it,is pratically everything.
我总认为古铜色的窗帘透露着神圣的气息
And I've always thought copper coloured curtains would be simply divine.
你们不觉得它们在日落时显得很美吗?
Don't you think they look rather lovely in the setting sun?
- 你想买点吗 埃尔莎? - 不需要
- Are you thinking of buying any,Elsa? - That won't be necessary.
你把我搞糊涂了 亲爱的
You seem to have lost me,my dear.
你这一切的装傻
All this pretense,
太不诚实了
it's so dishonest.
艾米亚斯和我彼此相爱 我们马上要结婚了
Amyas and I love each other and we're going to be married,
所以我会搬进来
so I shall be moving in.
就像我怀疑的一样 亲爱的
As I suspected,my dear,
你简直是个疯子
you're completely insane.
这该死的浓汤弄得我消化不良
That bloody bisque gave me a frightful indigestion.
找斯普里格斯太太吧 她会给你苏打水
Ask mrs. Spriggs,she'll give you bicarbonate of soda.
好主意
Good thinking.
另外 埃尔莎说你想和她结婚
By the way,Elsa says you want to marry her.
是真的吗?
Is this true?
- 是真的吗? - 她知道才公平
- Is it true? - It's only fair that she should know.
艾米亚斯 是真的吗?
Amyas,is it true?
这么说 是真的
Then,it is.
失陪 我去...
If you'll excuse me,I'll just...
回想起来
You know,looking back,
如果她决定要杀他 我也并不惊讶
I wouldn't be surprised if she had made up her mind to kill him then.
艾米亚斯 赶紧穿衣服
Amyas,do tide yourself up.
我们要去梅雷迪斯家喝茶 记得吗?
We're going up to Meredith for tea,remember?
- 啊 是啊 我给忘了 - 菲利浦
- Ahn,yes,I'd forgotten. - Philip,
你应该去钓钓鱼 海里也许有很多马鲛鱼
you should do some fishing while you're here. The sea's probably sworming with mackerel.
所以 我们都去了梅雷迪斯家
So,we all trooped off to Merri's.
但那天下午闹得不太愉快
Weren't very merry that afternoon...
艾米亚斯不能这么做!
Amyas can't do this!
看起来他打算这么做
Looks like he's going to.
他不能因为一个无知少女就抛妻弃子
He can't just leave his wife and child for some slip of a girl.
她还太小 不知道她在做什么
She's too young to know what she's doing.
她非常明白
She knows all right.
可怜的梅雷迪斯 他的担心根本没用
Poor old Merri,all that sensitivity no use at all.
真不敢相信他是和我们一起玩大的
Hard to believe we come from the same stable.
喝过茶后 我们来到他的实验室
After tea,he took us to his lab.
毒参 我从没听说过
Conium. I've never heard of this.
是由带斑的毒芹中蒸馏出来的
It's distilled from the flowers of the spotted hemlock.
有剧毒 但中毒后可以解救
Highly poisonous,but can be efficacious in the treatment...
抱歉
Sorry.
他给我们念了解救方法
Then he had the treat to read us
讲了柏拉图 苏格拉底的死
some classical about the whole death of Plato or Socrates,
之类的
or someting whatnot.
"给他下毒的人捏了捏他的脚
"The man who administered the poison pinched his foot,
问他有没有感觉 苏格拉底说没有
"and asked if he felt. Socrates said no.
然后他又试了试他的腿
"Then he did the same to his legs,
就这样一直向上 以这种方式 让我们看到
"and gradually moving up,and led us this way,and let us see
他全身冰冷麻木
"that he was cold and numb.
他说当毒液到达心脏
"He said that,when it reached the heart,
苏格拉底就会死去
Socrates would be gone."
回去的那晚
Back at HQ,that evening,
艾米亚斯和安吉拉因为什么事吵得很厉害
Amyas and Angela had a God-all Mighty row about someting,
但并无大碍
but nothing out of the ordinary.
我记得她好像朝他扔了什么东西
I even think she might have thrown something at thim.
- 你能想起来是什么吗? - 天啊 不能
- Can you remember what? - Good Lord,no.
- 那可是14年前的事情 - 没错 当然
- It was 14 years ago! - But yes,of course.
您的话对我很有帮助 布莱克先生
You are being most helpful,Monsieur Blake.
第二天早上 我下楼的时候
The next morning,when I came downstairs,
听见艾米亚斯和凯若琳在书房
I heard Amyas and Caroline in the library.
不知道他们哪来的精力
I don't know where they the energy from.
我发誓!
...I swear to God!
你和你的女人!
You and your women!
总有一天我会杀了你 艾米亚斯
Someday I'll kill you,Amyas.
- 别傻了 - 我向天发誓 我会的!
- Don't be idiot. - I swear to God,I will!
早上好
Good morning.
- 天气真不错! - 我要继续
- Lovely day! - I want to get on.
我去换衣服
I'll go change.
别太久了 该死的女人!
Don't be long. Bloody women!
然后他走了 回去画画 我进了屋
And off he went,back to his painting while I went back inside.
- 早上好 - 太残忍了 太残忍了
- Good morning. - It's too cruel,too cruel.
她根本没看到我
She hardly noticed me.
现在 当然 我知道为什么
Now,of course,I know why.
喂?
Hello?
见鬼 怎么了?
What the hell's the matter?
我听见实验室里有声音
I heard these noises from the laboratory...
我看了看装毒参的瓶子
... so,I went to have a look and the conium bottle
不但被动过了 而且空了
was not only out of place,but was practically empty.
我向你发誓 昨天它还是满的
And I swear to you,Phil,that yesterday it was full.
- 你确定吗? - 当然确定!
- Are you sure? - Of course I'm sure!
我很小心的保管这些东西的
I'm very careful about these things.
我当时就想到一定是凯若琳
And I knew at once it must have been Caroline.
我应该马上找艾米亚斯提醒他的
I should've gone straight to Amyas and warned him.
太荒唐了 凯若琳怎么会这么做
That's absurd. Caroline wouldn't dream of such a thing.
- 那你怎么解释? - 对她太残酷了
- Then,what's your explanation ? - ..being too harsh with her.
- 天啊! - 午饭后再说这事
- For God's sake! - We'll discuss after lunch.
我去帮她打包
I'll see to her packing...
- 你们在干什么? - 我们...
- What are you two up to ? - We were just...
- 哦 你们也在! - 是的
- What a surprise! - Yes...
我们刚刚在谈安吉拉和学校的事
We're just having a little chat about Angela and school.
我觉得还有不妥的地方
I'm not sure at all it is the right thing.
很抱歉
Sorry about that.
- 大家好! - 我真想来杯冰啤酒
- Hello everybody! - I'd kill for a cold beer.
我去拿些来
I'll send some down.
我想我们都得来一杯
I think we all could do with one.
就在这时 事情发生了
And that's when it happened.
我来吧?
Why don't I take it?
哦 不! 你们好好晒太阳
Oh,no! Enjoy the sun.
当时 我觉得是女人吃醋
At the time,I reasoned that it might be jealousy,
她受不了他们两个单独在一起
That she couldn't stand the thought of the two of them being alone together.
我早就应该意识到 但是 我只是坐在那看着
I should've realized,but,instead I sat and watched.
我本应有机会救他 但我什么也没做
I had the chance to save him,and I did nothing.
您过于自责了 布莱克先生
You reproach yourself unduly,Monsieur Blake.
艾米亚斯没来吃午饭
Amyas didn't join us for lunch,
凯若琳给他送咖啡
and Caroline took him cofee.
如此镇定 泰然自若
so calm and collected,and yet,
她一定知道他已经死了
she must have known by then he'd be dead.
威廉斯小姐跟她一起去的 然后梅雷迪斯
Miss Williams went with her,and then Meredith...
走开了 但是我们很快又看到他了
... wandered off,but it wasn't long before we saw him again.
叫医生! 赶快!
Get a doctor! Quick!
怎么了?
What's wrong?
- 是艾米亚斯... - 怎么了?
- It's Amyas... - What?
恐怕他死了
I'm affraid he's dead.
艾米亚斯!
Amyas!
给医生打电话 我来照顾她
Phone a doctor. I'll take care of her.
她一脸的愤怒 我从没见过
She was like an Avenging Fury. I had never seen anything  like it.
你杀了他! 你杀的! 我的艾米亚斯!
You killed him! You killed...! My Amyas!
- 你杀死了我最好的朋友! - 不!
- You've killed my dearest friend! - No!
- 是他自己做的 - 留着跟警察说吧
- He did it to himself. - Tell that to the police.
警察也不相信她
They didn't believe her either.
是的 布莱克先生
Eh bien,Monsieur Blake,
真相总会浮出水面的
The truth,it has the habit of revealing itself.
波罗先生
Monsieur Poirot...
迪蒂斯汉姆女士
Lady Dittisham...
我们开始吧 好吗?
Let's get on with it,shall we?
很多年前 克雷尔一案 我该说的都说了
I said all I had to say about the Crale Case many years ago.
但我对你的信很感兴趣
But I found your letter rather intriguing.
你就这么想见我?
How lucky you are curiosity took the better of me.
事实上 是的 夫人
Indeed I am,milady.
也许回忆过去对你来说很痛苦
It must be very painful for you to recall.
痛苦? 不
Painful? No.
我爸爸就是个直来直去的人
My father was a manhandled
用自己的方式赚了一大笔
who worked his way up and made a Mint.
这点事怎么能伤害到我 我可是我爸的女儿
You can't do that with thin skin in eye,I'm my father's daughter.
我没有你想象的那么敏感
I am not as sensitive as you might think.
那就好办了
Then that makes my task a little easier.
人们总是得出错误的结论
One so often jumps to the wrong conclusion.
比如在法庭上
At the trial,for example,
人们认为那对我来说是莫大的折磨
people thought what a terrible ordeal it must have been for me:
那些残酷的问题 可怕的记者
the brutish questions,the ghastly jornalists,
还有那些无知的尖叫人们
the mindless screaming crowd.
但是英国人是很讲究道德的 不是吗?
But the english are a people very moral,n'est-ce pas?
那只是某些人的看法
That's one way of looking at it.
那么 如果你觉得审判不是折磨
Alors, if you did not find the trial an ordeal,
- 那你怎么认为? - 我很享受
- how do you find it? - I enjoyed it.
我得到了我想要的
You see,I got exactly what I wanted.
你想要什么?
And what was that?
绞刑架上的凯若琳・克雷尔
Caroline Crale at the end of a rope.
要咖啡吗?
Coffee?
谢谢 蒂平
Thank you,Tipping.
你的信中说...
You said in your letter that Mademoiselle...
- 莱马钱特小姐 - 没错
- Lemarchant. - That's right.
她让你调查此事 我不认识她
Had commissioned you. I don't believe I know her.
她是艾米亚斯和凯若琳・克雷尔的女儿
She is the daughter of Amyas and Caroline Crale.
哦 是的! 当然 是有个孩子
Oh,yes! Of course. There was a child.
噢 天啊! 她认为是我的错?
Oh,dear! Does she think it was my fault?
这么说也对 没错
It is a possible interpretation,oui.
- 真愚蠢 要奶精吗? - 不 不 谢谢
- How very stupid. Cream? - Non,non. Merci.
您觉得您没有责任?
So,you take no responsability?
为什么? 我爱他 我能让他快乐
Why should I? I loved him,and I would've made him happy.
那个女人却杀了她来阻止我俩
And that woman killed him to stop that from happening.
要知道 艾米亚斯・克雷尔没有勾引无知少女
You have to understand,Amyas Crale did not seduce an innocent young girl.
绝对没有
It wasn't like that at all.
埃尔莎・格里尔
Elsa Greer.
我看到他第一眼 就决定要拥有他
As soon as I laid eyes on him,I knew I had to have him.
- 我想让你画我 - 我不画肖像画
- I want you to paint me. - I don't do portraits.
我有的是钱 我付得起
I'm rather rich,you know? I can afford to pay.
你为什么觉得我会想画你?
And what makes you think I'd want to paint you?
但是你确实想 不是吗?
But you do,don't you?
我总能得到我想要的
And I always get what I want.
那 我们什么时候开始呢?
So,when do we start?
如果我画你 你知道你要献出身体吗?
If I paint you,you realise I'll make love to you?
不用说我也知道
I'd have thought that went without saying.
然后他大胆的邀请我到他家
So,he invited me down to their house,quite bold of him,really.
但凯若琳好像不在意
But Caroline didn't seem to mind.
她不喜欢我 当然了 为什么要喜欢我?
She didn't like me,but then,why should she?
我们绝不说她可能听到的话
And  we never said anything that she couldn't have overheard.
但是我们察觉到了一些事情
But we were more than aware of what was going on.
怎么了?
What is it?
我想你应该回伦敦了
I think you ought to go back to London.
但是画... 我们还没开始
But the picture... we've hardly started.
我不能画你 埃尔莎
I can't paint you,Elsa.
- 为什么? - 你知道为什么
- Why? - You know why.
所以 我走了 没写信 没打电话
So,I left. I didn't write,or telephone.
十天之后...
And after 10 days...
他忘不了我 我们在一起待了两周
He couldn't keep away. We were together for two weeks
我们很快意识到我们必须在一起
and soon we realised that we had to be together.
- 永远在一起 - 我要你回到阿德博瑞
- Always. - I want you to come back to Alderbury.
我决定完成那幅画
I've decided to finish the painting.
- 那凯若琳怎么办? - 什么?
- What about Caroline? - What about her?
- 我们要告诉她吗? - 为什么?
- Shouldn't you tell her? - What on earth for?
她迟早会发现
She's bound to find out,sooner or later.
我们先完成那幅画再说
We'll get the picture finished first.
你会告诉她 对吗?
But you will tell her,won't you?
- 是的 - 你发誓?
- Yes. - Promise?
我发誓
Promise.
你想没想过她会很生气?
Do you think she'll make a terrible fuss?
她总是很生气
She always makes a fuss.
她爱我
She loves me.
那她就应该以你的幸福为先
Then she should put your happiness first.
他全身投入绘画 我从没见过他这样
He painted in a kind of frenzy. I'd never seen like that before.
别动 老天!
- Keep still,for God's sake!
我觉得我们应该告诉她
I was convinced we should tell her,
但艾米亚斯不听 直到有一天 我失去了耐心
but Amyas wouldn't hear of it. Then,one day,I... lost my patience.
艾米亚斯相爱 我们要结婚
Amyas and I love each other and we are going to be married.
我会搬进来
So I shall be moving in.
艾米亚斯很抓狂
Amyas was furious
但他得承认我说的是事实
but he had to admit what I said was true.
我现在仍觉得我是对的
And I still think I was right.
诚实是最好的对策 你说呢 波罗先生?
Honesty is,after all the best policy,don't you agree Mr Poirot?
当然 但并不总是这样
Desirable,certainly,but not always advisable.
我说过我是个直来直去的人
We believe in plain speaking,where I come from.
听到这我很高兴 女士
I'm very pleased to hear it,Madame.
但是凯若琳表现很怪异
But Caroline had a devious way about her.
那天中午我们去梅雷迪斯家喝茶
When we went to Meredith for tea,that afternoon,
她表现的像什么事都没发生过
she behaved as if nothing had happened.
我甚至以为她接受了事实
I even began to think she was taking it rather well.
我真是错的离谱!
How wrong I was!
请您告诉我 迪蒂斯汉姆女士
If you please to tell me,Lady Dittisham,
实话实说
in plain speaking,
你们在布莱克先生实验室的时候
if,when you were all assembled in the laboratory of Monsieur Blake,
你注意到凯若琳拿走那瓶毒参吗?
you observed Caroline Crale take the conium.
没有
No,I did not.
我只记得和梅雷迪斯在门口聊天
I seem to remember chatting with Meredith in the doorway,
- 所以我没看见 - 凯若琳
so I wouldn't have been able to see a thing. - Caroline...
抱歉 梅雷迪斯 这收藏太有趣啦
Sorry,Merri. It's such a fascinanting collection...
但是她当然拿了 我们都知道为什么
But of course she did take it,and we all know why.
不是每个人都像你那么确信
Perhaps not everyone is as sure as you.
我还听到她威胁他
I actually heard her threatening him.
你和你的女人!
You and your women!
总有一天 我会杀了你 艾米亚斯
Someday I'll kill you,Amyas.
- 别傻了 - 我对天发誓 我会杀了你
- Don't be an idiot. - I swear to God I'll kill you.
随你怎么威胁我 但你要明白
You can threaten all you like,but get this,
我就是要和埃尔莎结婚 谁也阻止不了
I'm going to marry Elsa and nothing is going to stop me.
- 我杀了你也不会让你走 - 早上好
- I'll kill you rather than let you go. - Morning.
天啊!
For God's sake!
- 天气不错! - 我要继续
- Lovely day! - I want to get on.
- 我去换衣服 - 别太久
- I'll go change. - Don't be long.
我没花很久 然后我去找他 给他倒了杯啤酒
Which I did. Then,I went to join him and I poured him a beer.
她很生气
She's making a terrible song and dance.
我告诉过你的
Told you she would.
- 敬我的蒙娜丽莎 - 我亲爱的艾米亚斯
- To my Mona Lisa. - My darling Amyas.
- 天啊 是热的! - 我去拿冰的
- God,it's warm! - I can get you a cold one.
坐下! 坐下!
On that seat. Sit down,now!
他好像是用他的生命为我画画
He painted as if his life depended on it.
亲爱的艾米亚斯
Dear Amyas...
我是如此爱他
I loved him so much...
不一会事情就发生了 我去房间取围巾
It happened shortly after that. I popped up to the house to fetch a shawl,
我回来的时候 她在那
and,when I came back,she was there.
抱歉
Sorry about that.
大家好!
Hello everybody!
- 我想来杯冰啤酒 - 我去拿点
- I'd kill for a cold beer. - I'll send some down.
她一定知道她接下来要做什么
She must have known then what she meant to do.
10分钟后她拿着啤酒过来
She brought it back about 10 minutos later.
真难喝!
Tastes foul!
今天的东西怎么都这么难喝
Everything tastes foul,today.
太多怒气了 亲爱的
Too much bile,my dear.
那总有一天会要你的命的
It'll choke you,one of these days.
我没怀疑什么 大约40分钟后
I didn't suspect a thing. About 40 minutes later,
- 他抱怨着这疼那疼 - 该死的风湿!
- he complained about stiffness and pains. - Bloody rheumatism!
然后午饭的铃声响了 梅雷迪斯叫我去吃饭
Then,the bell sounded for lunch and Meredith came to fetch me.
艾米亚斯说不吃了 像往常一样
Amyas decided to skip lunch,as he often did.
那个暴脾气说他不吃午餐了
Old grumpy doesn't want any lunch.
然后我们离开了
So we left him...
他一个人 死了
... to die alone.
艾米亚斯! 艾米亚斯!
Amyas! Amyas!
我就知道是凯若琳干的
And I just knew it was Caroline.
她怎么能这样? 她怎么能?
How could she do that? How could she?
这真是个...
It is a story most...
悲剧啊 不是吗?
... tragique,n'est-ce pas?
绞刑对她太宽容了
Hanging was too good for her.
布莱克先生
Monsieur Blake...
小露西
Little Lucy...
长大了 真不敢相信
... a grown woman. One can hardly believe it.
- 时光飞逝啊 不是吗? - 可怜的孩子
- Time passes swiftly,does it not? - Poor child.
对她来说打击不小 这样也许更好
Such a terrible shock. How much better to let it all be.
艾米亚斯・克雷尔是个艺术家
The whole point,you see,is that Amyas Crale was an artist,
他对艺术充满热情
and his art was his passion.
他画画的时候就像着了魔
When he painted,he was like a man-- possessed.
他打算不惜一切完成那幅画
He meant to finish that portrait,whatever the cost.
埃尔莎很热衷于画画 凯若琳...
Elsa was terrifically enthusiastic about the painting,and Caroline...
- 怎么了? - 我一直...
- Yes? - I had always been...
...非常喜欢她
... very fond of her.
快来 梅雷迪斯 过来!
Come on,Merri,come on!
我曾经想过要娶她
There was a time when I'd hoped to marry her,
虽然很快就放弃了
but that was soon nipped in the bud.
但我仍然愿意
Still I remained,if I may say so,
为她做任何事
devoted to her service.
天哪!
Dear God!
她那时遭受到了怎样的待遇啊!
When I think of what they did to her!
像牲口一样被捆起来!
Strung up like an animal!
那样的一个美人...
Such a gentle creature...
我记得事情发生不久 我们有过一次对话
I remember a conversation we had shortly after it all began.
你觉得他真的在乎她吗?
Do you think he really cares for her?
呃 他只是为了画出更好的画而已
Well,he's very committed to the painting.
他爱上她了 不是么?
He's in love with her,isn't he?
可能有一点点吧
A little,perhaps.
我觉得不止一点点
A great deal,I think.
他唯一在乎的人 是你
There's only one person he reallly cares for,I think that's you.
这些迷恋 很快就过去了
These infatuations,they come and they go.
我以前也是这么想的
That's what I used to think.
但是这次 我感觉他是认真的
But this time I've a feeling it's serious.
- 她只是个小女孩 - 这就是问题关键
- She's just a girl. - That's the trouble.
瞧她看他时的眼神!
The way she looks at him!
那么炽热!
So intense!
我很害怕 梅雷迪斯
I'm affraid,Meredith.
没什么的
It's nothing.
希望你是对的 但我
I hope you're right. But I can't help feeling
真想一短斧劈死她
I'd like to take a hatchet to her.
- 短斧? - 就是小斧头
- A hatchet? - It's a small ax.
我知道短斧是什么 我是在对她的话表示惊讶
I know what a hatchet is. I was commenting rather on her remark.
她就是随口说说
It was merely to make her point.
那她说得也太狠了吧
She made her point a little more forcibly,
太狠了 不是吗?
forcibly,did she not?
正如她对她的小妹妹安吉拉的所作所为
With her baby sister Angela,
- 你说纸镇那个事? - 是的
- The paperweight. - Oui.
那只是姐妹间的嫉妒 她为这事一直自责着
It was a moment of sibling's jealousy for which she never forgave herself.
然后毁了一个女孩的一生
And disfigured a girl for life.
这就是问题所在 她无法释怀
That was the problem. It was a constant reminder,
她想尽一切办法弥补她
and she tried desperatly to make amends,
反而让艾米亚斯吃醋了
which,in turn,made Amyas very jealous.
你与他相识很多年了 是吧?
You knew him for many years,n'est-ce pas?
我们是发小
Since boyhood.
不过菲利浦和他关系更好
But he was always more Philip's friend than mine.
你不喜欢他?
You did not like him?
我觉得他行为不检
I think his conduct was frankly disgraceful.
你不明白吗?
Don't you understand?
这幅画是我最成功的一次 我一定要完成它
This painting is the best thing I've done and I'm determined to see it through.
不 我觉得这实在是不得体...
No. I think it's a disgrace...
你不该那样对凯若琳 你总是这样对她
... the way you treat Caroline. The way you've always treated her.
露西怎么办? 你总不能抛下一切
What about Lucy,for Heaven's sake? You can't just throw it all away.
你是个好人 梅雷迪斯 不过你管太多了
You're a good man,Merri,but such a old softy.
等我的画完成了 你就知道我是对的了
Wait til the picture is finished then you'll see I was right.
他对我咧嘴一笑...
That grin he gave me...
我永远也忘不了那天下午的凯若琳
I'll never forget Caroline,that afternoon.
她努力装作无所谓 但坚强外表之下...
She made such an effort,and yet,behind it all...
怎么了吗 心爱的?
Is there anything the matter,my dear?
一切...都没了
Everything. It's gone.
结束了
Finished.
当她在法庭上说她拿走毒药是为了自杀时
When she said,at the trial,that she took the poison to kill herself,
我发誓她没有说谎
I swear she was speaking the truth.
不过你为什么要把客人带去实验室呢?
But why did you take your guests into the laboratory?
一定是有人提议的
Someone must have sugested it.
是不是凯若琳・克雷尔呢?
Caroline Crale,perhaps?
我经常带客人去实验室 这很正常
Well,I often took guests into my laboratory. It wasn't unusual.
- 这是缬草液 - 就是猫很喜欢的那个?
- This is valerian. - The one that cats like.
没错 它们超爱这味道 这个还有安眠的作用
Yes,they can't get enough of it. It can be used as a sleeping draft.
埃尔莎 给你闻闻
Elsa,You should have a sniff.
我乐此不疲地进行研究药草
I've amount pleasure from my brews,
在晚上收集药草 进行浸泡什么的
gatherring the plants at night,macerating and all the rest of it..
简简单单的药草能变得大有用途
It's astonishing
这太让人惊异了
how a simple decoction can make wonders.
毒参 我从来没听过这个
Conium. I've never heard of this.
是由带斑的毒芹中蒸馏出来的
It's distilled from the flowers of the spotted hemlock.
是不是就是苏格拉底喝下的那个毒药?
Isn't that what Socrates took?
没错
That's right.
在柏拉图的中有十分动人的描述
You know,there's the most moving description of his death on Plato's "Phaedo".
你们想听的话我可以读给你们听
I can read it to you if you'd like.
抱歉 抱歉 太热了就犯困
Sorry. Sorry,it must be the heat.
"给他下毒的人捏了捏他的脚
"The man who administered the poison pinched his foot,
"问他有没有感觉 苏格拉底说没有
"and asked if he felt anything. Socrates said no.
"然后他又试了试他的腿
"Then,he did the same to his legs,
"就这样一直向上 以这种方式 让我们看到
"gradually moving upwards,showing us this way and letting us
"他全身冰冷麻木
"see that he was getting cold and numb.
"他说 当毒性扩散到心脏
"He said that when it reached the heart,
苏格拉底就会死去"
Socrates would be gone."
而这正是第二天...
And that is how Amyas met his fate...
艾米亚斯的命运
... the very next day.
克雷尔夫人是什么时候从瓶子里拿到毒参的?
When did Madame Crale take the conium from the bottle?
就是在她去研究区之前...
Just before she came into the study area...
好像菲利浦和安吉拉先走了
I think Philip and Angela left first,
然后是艾米亚斯 我站在门口 等着锁门
followed by Amyas. I was in the doorway,waiting to lock up,
我跟埃尔莎说了几句话
having a word with Elsa.
我觉得她就是那时候拿的
I supose that's when she took it.
- 凯若琳 - 噢 抱歉 梅雷迪斯
- Caroline. - Oh sorry,Merri.
这收藏太有趣啦
Such a fascinating collection...
菲利浦? 我是梅雷迪斯 出事了
Phil? It's Meredith. Something terrible's happened.
他立刻就怀疑是凯若琳
He immediately suspected Caroline.
我觉得这不公平
Quite unfairly,in my opinion.
还能有谁? 绝对是凯若琳
Who else could have done it? It must have been Caroline.
我们往水景园走的时候
As we approached the water garden,
碰巧听到艾米亚斯和凯若琳
we overheard Amyas and Caroline
在很激烈地争吵什么
having a rather heated discussion,
我想应该是把安吉拉送去学校的事
I think about Angela being packed off to school.
这样做太无耻了!
It's such a shameful behaviour!
我当时心里很乱 没太注意听
I was in such a state I didn't pay it much atention.
那就这样 我去帮她打包
It's settled. I'll see to her packing.
菲利浦为没有马上采取行动而自责
Philip blamed himself for not acting sooner,
不过那时又有谁能想到
but how on earth could anyone have assumed,
这会演变成一场谋杀呢?
at that point,that someone had murder in mind?
我需要时间来思考
I needed time to think.
所以上午一直坐在水景园那边
So,just before lunch,I sat above the water garden
艾米亚斯在那里画埃尔莎
where Amyas was painting Elsa.
我能摆出罗马皇后坐在竞技场的坐姿
... and I can sit like like a Roman Emperess in the Coliseum.
那么耀眼
So radiant,
充满生命力
full of life,
是我认识的最有活力的人了
more alive than any person I have ever known.
- 别动! - 年轻的盲目自信
- Keep still! - The blind confidence of youth.
- 该死的风湿! - 可怜的人啊!
- Bloody rheumatism! - Poor thing!
那个暴脾气说他不吃午餐了
Old grumpy doesn't want any lunch.
问题是 他画画时经常这样
The problem was,he often looked like that when he was working,
所以我也没多想
so I didn't think anything of it.
- 埃尔莎... - 我饿得能吃下一头牛
- Elsa... - I could eat a horse.
我真的希望...
You know,I do so wish...
什么?
What?
你和艾米亚斯别再这样了
Well,that you and Amyas would stop it. Just stop it.
他有妻儿 他必须对她们负责
He has a wife and child. His place is with them.
噢 梅雷迪斯...
Oh,Meredith...
午饭过后 大家在阳台上喝咖啡
After lunch,they had coffee on the terrace.
凯若琳去给艾米亚斯拿啤酒
Caroline took a cup down to Amyas,
威廉斯夫人和她一起去的
and Miss Williams accompanied her.
稍后我也离开了 好像是去...
I followed shortly afterwards,I think to...
...饭后散步 - 布莱克先生!
... walk off my lunch. - Mr. Blake!
- 布莱克先生! - 怎么了?
- Mr. Blake! - What's wrong?
- 不得了了! - 到底怎么了?
- A terrible thing! - What on earth is it?
克雷尔先生... 死了
Mr. Crale... He's dead.
你能去叫个医生来吗?
Would you be so kind as to call a doctor?
天啊!
My God!
去叫医生! 快!
Get a doctor! Quick!
- 怎么了? - 是艾米亚斯...
- What? - It's Amyas.
- 怎么了? - 他好像死了...
- What? - I'm affraid he's dead.
艾米亚斯!
Amyas!
可怜的孩子
Poor child.
她怎么也无法相信
She just couldn't believe
老天爷会开如此残酷的玩笑吧
that life could play so cruel a trick.
凯若琳站在那儿 很平静 说他一定是自杀
Caroline stood there,quite calmly,and said he must've done it to himself.
所以 先生 你很肯定她是有罪的?
So,you are perfectly convinced,Monsieur,that she was guilty?
她也是被逼无奈
She was provoked,in the extreme.
但是你觉得这不是自杀?
But you do not believe it was suicide?
是凯若琳干的 我敢肯定
Caroline did it,I'm sure of it.
不过
And anyway,
如果她没杀人呢...
what if she didn't...
我是赫尔克里・波罗 夫人
Hercule Poirot,Mademoiselle.
露西・克雷尔...
Lucy Crale...
你最后一次看到她时 她还很小
She must have been very young When you last saw her.
七岁半
Seven and a half.
很迷人
Charming.
她有点内向 活在自己的小世界里
A little too quiet. Lived in a world of her own.
夫人 我想请问您
If you tell to me,please,Mademoiselle,
她的父母 他们很相爱 是吗?
her parents,they were most devoted,yes?
波罗先生 很少会有
One does occasionally find,Monsieur Poirot,
像他们那么相爱的夫妇了
a husband and wife so wrapped up in each other
连孩子都没能分走他们的爱
that the child hardly seems to impinge.
更像恋人而不是夫妇?
So,more like lovers than husband and wife?
你想这么说也行
If that's how you wish to put it.
你喜欢克雷尔夫人吗?
Did you like Madame Crale?
是的 我非常喜欢她
Yes,I was very fond of her.
那你的学生呢?
And your pupil?
安吉拉是个很有意思的女孩 尽管有些难相处
Angela was a most interesting if difficult girl.
我很欣慰在她的成功道路上帮了她一把
I cherish the belief that I've played a modest part in her success.
你读过她写的吗?
Have you read her book of the tombs in the Fayum?
很遗憾 没有
Sadly,non.
写得非常好 建议你去看看
It's compelling stuff. Read it.
啊 好的 我会的...
I guess. Yes,I  shall...
她被送去学校时你一定很难过吧
You must have been upset when she was sent away to school.
不 不 一点也不
No,no,not at all.
对她来说 在家的日子实在算不上"理想"
To her,home life was hardly what would turn "ideal" .
凯若琳很宠她 艾米亚斯对此感到嫉妒
Caroline indulged her,Amyas got jealous,
他和安吉拉经常吵架
he and Angela would fight,
然后她会报复性地对他恶作剧
and she'd end up playing some spiteful trick.
即使这样 也比那些行为好多了
And though,of course,far greater actions prevailed.
你是在说埃尔莎・格里尔?
You mean Elsa Greer?
正是
Exactly.
你觉得她是个怎样的人?
What was your opinion of her?
她完全没有道德
She was thoroughly unprincipled.
不过她确实很爱艾米亚斯
And also very much in love.
他的死一定深深地打击了她
His death must have been for her a shock most terrible.
- 这都要怪她 - 格里尔小姐吗?
- And it was entirely her fault. - Mademoiselle Greer?
是她让事情变成那样的 她居然脸皮厚到
The way she carried on. She even had the insolence
说她和艾米亚斯要结婚
to suggest they were going to marry.
她知道了才公平
It's only fair that she should know.
艾米亚斯 她说的是不是真的?
Amyas,is it true?
这么说 是真的
Then,it is.
她给他的表情! 那么高尚!
The look she gave him! Magnificent!
然后她走了出去 高昂着头
And then she walked out,head held high,
仍然那么优雅有风度
her grace and dignity unsolid.
她知道你这么欣赏她吗?
Was she aware of how much you admired her?
我想...
I believe...
我希望... 我充分表达了...
I hope that... I adequately expressed my...
我对她的支持
... my support for her.
克雷尔夫人...
Mrs. Crale...
让我一个人待会 威廉斯女士
Not now,Miss Williams.
我只是想告诉你...
I just meant to tell...
让我一个人静静 拜托
Another time,please.
好的 当然 抱歉
Yes,of course. I'm sorry.
我认为你非常优秀
I think you're wonderful.
噢 但你不知道...
Oh,but you don't know...
然后呢 夫人?
And then,Mademoiselle?
然后大家去梅雷迪斯・布莱克家中喝咖啡了
And then,they all went to tea at Meredith Blake's.
那天晚上 晚饭过后 争吵又开始了
And that evening,after dinner,the usual arguments began
关于把安吉拉送去学校一事
about Angela and school.
你听着! 学费已经交了 校服已经买了
Now,you listen! The fees are payed the uniform's bought,
这事定了! - 我不去!
case closed! - I'm not going!
是个非常好的学校 亲爱的
It's a lovely school,darling.
就在唐斯中部地区
It's right in the middle of the Downs.
你一定能交到许多好朋友的
I'm sure that you'll make lots of nice friends.
我不要什么朋友
I don't want any friends.
要是你一直这样的话 那一个朋友也交不到
You won't get any,if you carry on like this.
你们为什么要把我赶走?
Why do you want to get rid of me?
没人想赶走你 你知道我们爱你
Nobody wants to get rid of you. You know we all love you.
他才不爱我! 他根本就不想再见到我了
He doesn't! He won't care if he doesn't see me again.
没错! 你叫得跟个泼妇似的!
Right! All this screaming like a fishwife...
你不是就喜欢泼妇么!
You know all about them!
听着 小屁孩...
Now,look here,girlie...
- 你去死吧! - 安吉拉!
- I wish you were dead! - Angela!
我跟着安吉拉去了她的房间
I followed Angela to her room
然后严厉地批评了她
and reprehended her sharply.
第二天早上天气很好
The next morning was so beautiful
我乐观地想这或许会使我们的生活重回平静
that I fondly thought it might restore some peace to our lives.
却不知道这是暴风雨前的宁静
Little did I know it was the harbinger of murder.
安吉拉!
Angela!
安吉拉又一次不见人影 我以为她是去游泳了
Angela had yet again disappeared,I thought for a swim,
不过在河边没找到她 所以 我又回到房子里
but there were no signs of her. So,I returned to the house.
克雷尔夫人正要为大家在午饭前上些啤酒
Mrs. Crale was about to serve some beer before lunch,
我去帮她
so I offered to help her.
我们去了地下室 那里被用作冰窖
We went to the cellar,which was used to cold storage.
等我们到了那 却看到安吉拉形迹可疑
As we arrived,we found Angela,behaving in a most suspicious manner.
- 你在这里做什么? - 我只是...
- What on earth are you doing with that? - I was just...
你不会是想喝酒吧
I hope you weren't thinking of drinking it.
我来拿吧 好吗
I'll take,if you don't mind.
你能把酒端给其他人吗?
Would you mind serving the others?
我下去把这个给艾米亚斯
I'll pop this down to Amyas.
而在这期间
And all this time
埃尔莎一直坐着让克雷尔先生画画?
Mlle. Greer was sitting for Monsieur Crale?
是的
Yes.
噢 他真是活该
Oh,he got what he deserved.
他确实做得不对 没错
He acted very badly,oui,c'est vrai.
但他是个...
But he was...
很出色的艺术家 不是吗?
A great artiste,n'est-ce pas?
出色? 他根本就不会画画
Great? Couldn't even draw.
他的图画比例很糟糕 人体结构一团糟
His perspective was terrible,The anatomy was all over the place...
我知道我在说什么
I know what I'm talking about.
我小时候在佛罗伦萨学过艺术
I studied art,as a girl,in Florence.
请告诉我 夫人
Tell me,Mademoiselle,
克雷尔夫人发现尸体时
you were with Madame Crale
你和她在一起 是吗?
when she discovered the body,yes?
不 不在一起
No,not exactly.
午饭后 我们一起从房子里出来
We went down from the house together,after lunch.
她去给克雷尔先生送咖啡
She was taking Mr. Crale some coffee,
而我准备去河边找安吉拉的运动衣
and I was going to the beach to look for Angela's jersey.
艾米亚斯? 艾米亚斯!
Amyas? Amyas!
克雷尔先生?
Mrs. Crale?
艾米亚斯...
It's Amyas.
死了
He's dead.
布莱克先生! 布莱克先生!
Mr. Blake! Mr. Blake!
怎么了?
What's wrong?
我正好撞见梅雷迪斯・布莱克
I bumped into Meredith Blake,
告诉了他这个噩耗
told him the terrible news,
并让他打电话叫医生
and asked him to telephone the doctor.
我很担心克雷尔夫人
I was most concerned about Mrs. Crale,
我不想把她一个人丢在那里
I didn't want her to be left alone.
你觉得克雷尔夫人那时在想些什么呢?
Did you get an impression about what Madame Crale was thinking at the time?
看不出来 她完全呆住了
It was impossible to tell. She was stunned.
她对外是怎么看待他的死的?
What view did she adopt officially as to his death?
自杀
Suicide.
- 那私底下对你怎么说的? - 也是一样
- Even in private,to you? - She had no doubt whatsoever.
那你又是怎么对她说的呢?
And what did you say to her?
这椅子坐得不舒服吗 夫人?
Is that chair uncomfortable,Mlle.?
不是 非常舒服 谢谢
It's perfectly comfortable,thank you.
你还没告诉我...
You were about to tell me...
我好像是这样说的...
I-I- I think I said,
"当然了 克雷尔夫人 一定是自杀"
"Certainly,Mrs. Crale,it must have been suicide" .
- 你相信是自杀吗? - 不 不相信
- Did you believe that? - No,I did not.
不过请你了解这一点
But understand this:
我是完全站在她这一边的
I was entirely on her side.
- 所以你希望她被无罪释放? - 当然
- So you'd have liked to see her acquited? - But of course I would.
那么高雅尊贵的女性
A woman of honor,of dignity,
却像肉店的肉一样被绞死!
hanged like a carcase in a butchershop!
可怜的露西! 不得不面对这一切!
Poor Lucy! Having to be confronted by all of this!
不过 面对真相总归是好的
Still,it is always better to face the truth.
不止这样 她想证明她母亲是无辜的
But there's more to it than that. She wants to prove her mother to be innocent.
那她的愿望恐怕要落空了
Then,her wish will not be granted.
凯若琳・克雷尔绞死前给她的女儿写了封信
Before she was hanged,Caroline Crale wrote to her daughter a letter
信里说自己是清白的
in which she solemny swears her inocence.
告诉她女儿不要指责她...
It would perhaps have been better...
...也许会更好
... to tell her daughter not to judge.
你似乎很确信她是有罪的
You seem very sure of her guilt.
别的说法也说不过去
It's hard to believe otherwise.
- 但你声称你爱她 - 我确实爱她
- And yet you profess to have loved her. - I did love her.
确实
I did.
可以结束了吧...
If that is all...
当然 当然
Yes,yes,of course.
感谢您能抽出时间 您的信息对我很有帮助
Thank you very much for your time,Mademoiselle. You have been most helpful.
我知道她是有罪的 先生
I know that she was guilty,Monsieur.
- 毫不怀疑 - 我能问为什么吗?
- Without a shadow of doubt. - May I ask how?
在遇到梅雷迪斯・布莱克并告诉他
After bumping into Meredith Blake
克雷尔先生的死讯后 我又回到了水景园
and informing him of Mr. Crale's death,I returned to the water garden.
我看到克雷尔夫人手忙脚乱
Mrs. Crale was not in command of herself,as I implied.
她脸上的恐惧告诉了我真相
It was the fear in her face that told me the truth.
所以我知道是她毒死了她的丈夫
That's when I knew she had poisoned her husband.
而我 并不怪罪她
And I,for one,do not blame her.
她不知道我看到了什么 我也没告诉她
She never knew what I'd seen,and I never told her.
事实上 我没告诉任何人
In fact,I never told anybody.
审讯期间 我也没被问到任何
During the trial,I was never asked a question
能让我撒谎的问题
to which I returned an untrue answer,
但因为掩盖一些事实 我有罪
but I was guilty of witholding certain facts.
但我不后悔 波罗先生
And I do not repent of that,Monsieur Poirot.
我还会那样做的
I would do so again.
...事实上和今天的社会一样的腐败和贪污
... was in fact such a corrupt and venal as the society of today.
从那时起 就有一些重要的挖掘物
Since then,there have been other key excavations,
但都比不上恰加尔巴扎尔的贡献 谢谢
but none as remarkable as Chagar Bazar. Thank you.
谢谢光临
Thank you so much for coming.
谢谢 谢谢
Thank you. Thank you.
我是赫尔克里・波罗 小姐
Hercule Poirot,Mademoiselle.
恰加尔巴扎尔的挖掘工作非凡之极
The Chagar Bazar digging was quite simply extraordinary.
你在国家地理上读到过我做的相关评论吗?
Did you read my account of it in the "National Geographic"?
很遗憾 没有 我还没有...
Sadly no. I have not yet...
相当权威
Fairly definitive,
如果能这么说的话
if I may say so myself.
小露西 我真想见见她
Little Lucy... I'd so like to see her.
你们没有保持联系吗?
You have not kept in contact?
没有 或者说联系很少
No,not nearly as much as I should've.
她想洗白她母亲的名声真是令人钦佩
I think it's admirable that she wants to clean her mother's name.
- 你赞成她的做法? - 当然了
- Then,you approve it? - Of course.
凯若琳是清白的 我一直相信
Caroline didn't do it. I've always known that.
您真让我大吃一惊 小姐
You surprise me,Mademoiselle.
每个跟我谈过话的人都...
Everyone else with whom I have spoken...
我知道 我知道
I know,I know.
现场铁证如山
The circumstantial evidence were overwhelming,
所以我从没想过这么做
that's frankly why I never tempted anything myself.
我非常了解我姐姐
I knew my sister extremely well
她绝对不会杀人
She quite simply couldn't have killed anyone.
但人的本性是多变的
The human nature has the infinite capacity to surprise .
但不会是在这种情况下
Not in this instance.
你为何如此确定?
How can you be so certain?
我就是确定
Because I am.
小姐 这个理由恐怕在法庭上站不住脚
But I'm affraid,Mademoiselle,that would not stand up in court.
这就是为什么我从未被传讯
That's why I was never called to give word in evidence.
如果你被传讯呢...
And if you had been...?
这就是我为什么知道的原因
This is why I know.
但对一些人来说 这证明的是相反的事
But for many,that would prove the exact opposite.
他们在审判中就是这么说的
As they claimed at the trial,
但这只是一时之怒
but this was a moment's rage
困扰了她一辈子 她一直没原谅自己
haunted her for the rest of her life. She never forgave herself,
所以 她总是保持警惕
as a result,she was constantly on her guard.
我不是说她温顺胆小 完全相反
I don't say she was meek or timid,quite the opposite,
但杀人? 不可能! 不可能!
but murder? Never! Never!
那是一个闲适的夏日
It was an idillic summer in so many ways...
据我的记忆是这样的
... what I can remember of it.
哦 露西 打我呀! 咱们玩的不就是这个么
Oh,come on,Lucy,do shoot me! That's all the point.
要是那个女人没有进入我们的生活
If only that woman didn't come into our lives...
你这一切的装傻
All this pretense,
太不诚实了
it's do dishonest.
艾米亚斯和我相爱 并且准备结婚
Amyas and I love each other and we're going to be married,
所以我会搬进来
so I should be moving in.
然后 当艾米亚斯出来时
Then,when Amyas came out...
为什么埃尔莎说她要跟你结婚?
Why did Elsa say she's going to marry you?
- 你怎么听到的? - 窗户开着
- And how did you hear that? - The window's open.
偷听是很无礼的
It's damned rude eavesdropping.
- 但她为什么那么说? - 那是个玩笑
- But why did she say it? - It was a joke.
- 对我来说不怎么好笑 - 够了 行吗?
- It's not very funny to me. - Enough,all right?!
过来 过来
Come on. Come on.
然后 在我们去梅雷迪斯家喝茶的路上
And then,on our way to tea at Meredith's,
我问凯若琳
I confronted Caroline.
- 是真的吗? - 什么 亲爱的?
- Is it true? - What,darling?
埃尔莎要和艾米亚斯结婚吗?
Is Elsa going to marry Amyas?
除非我死了
Only after I'm dead.
剩下的我记不清了
The rest of the day is blur.
好像梅雷迪斯读了些关于苏格拉底的优美文章
Kinda remember Meredith reading rather beautiful about Socrates...
"...他说当毒液到达心脏
" ... he said when it reached the heart,
苏格拉底就会死去
Socrates would be gone."
然后艾米亚斯和我在晚餐后又吵架了
... and then Amyas and I having a real humdinger after dinner.
听着 小屁孩!
Now look here,girlie!
我记得我朝他扔了什么东西
I think I threw something at him.
第二天 事发当天
And the next day,the day it happened,
也十分模糊
again it's all very vague,
直到梅雷迪斯气喘吁吁从小路上跑来
up until the point Merry came panting down the path.
我一直在对自己说 艾米亚斯死了
I kept saying to myself,"Amyas is dead" .
但那看起来不像真的
But it didn't seem real.
然后医生来了 警察来了 他们把他搬进房子
Then the doctor came,the police came,they brought him to the house.
我要你和露西去奶奶家
I want you to go to grandma's,with Lucy.
不 我不想去
No,no. I don't want to go.
- 我想和你在一起 - 我知道 亲爱的
- I want to stay with you. - I know,my darling,
但你最好去奶奶那 那样更容易 相信我
but it's best that you do. It'll easier that way,believe me.
不 求你了 我不想离开你
No,please,I don't want to leave you.
为了我 亲爱的 就为我去吧
For me,my darling,do it for me.
不要想今天的事
And you must try not to think about it.
没什么好担心的
There's nothing to worry about,
我保证
I promise.
那就是我最后一次见她
And that was the last time I ever saw her.
那个夏末...
The end of Summer...
...也是我童年的结束
... was the end of childhood.
几天后她被捕了
A few days later she was arrested.
我被送去德国上学
I was sent to school,in Germany,
露西被送到加拿大的亲戚处
Lucy was sent to relatives,in Canada.
就在她被绞死前
Just before she was hanged,
她留给我了封信 我从没给任何人看过
she wrote me a letter. I've never shown it to anyone.
我认为你该读读
I think you should read it.
谢谢 小姐
Merci,Mademoiselle.
"我亲爱的 安吉拉
"My darling Angela,
"我想让你知道一切都很好
"I want you to know that it is all alright.
"我从未向你撒谎
"I've never lied to you,
我说我现在很开心 这也是真的
and I don't now when I say that I'm happy,
我感到的是前所未有的宁静
that I feel a peace that I've never known before."
真是了不起
It's remarkable.
她是个了不起的人 她是无辜的
She was a remarkable person,and innocent.
但是信里并没有明确的这么说
But the letter does not say it explicitly.
因为不需要
Because it didn't to say it.
那么 你认为艾米亚斯・克雷尔是怎么死的?
Then,how do you think Amyas Crale died?
自杀
Suicide.
不觉得那与他的个性不符吗?
But is that not out of character?
你也说过
As you said before,
人性是多变的
human nature has an infinite capacity to surprise.
那么 你就不能找出其他解释吗?
Then,you can see no other explanation?
- 有人可能杀了他?  - 对
- You mean,someone else might have killed him? - Oui.
我觉得不太可能
I think it unlikely.
但是 如果
But if,for one second,
我们考虑一下这种可能 那么...
we consider the possibility,what then...
那我会说菲利浦・布莱克就是你要找的人
I would say Philip Blake might be your man.
我对此很感兴趣 小姐 我能问为什么吗?
Now,that interests me very much,mademoiselle. May I ask why?
我看不出他有什么潜在的动机
I cannot see what possible motive he could have.
他是艾米亚斯・克雷尔最好的朋友 不是吗?
He was the best friend of Amyas Crale,n'est-ce pas?
或者 他们俩是争夺埃尔莎的情敌?
Or were the two men rivals,perhaps,over Elsa?
不是埃尔莎
Not Elsa.
那个夏天的一个晚上
One night,that Summer,
我起床去浴室 当我打开门时
I got up,to get to the bathroom. And,as I opened the door,
我看到凯若琳从菲利浦的卧室里出来
I saw Caroline coming out from Philip's bedroom.
她脸上的表情 那时候我看不懂
She had a look on her face at the time I didn't really understand.
但回想起来...
But,looking back...
我对布莱克先生的印象是
I got the impression,
他好像并不怎么喜欢你姐姐
from Monsieur Blake,that always he disliked your sister.
我承认 我以前也有那么一点点恋爱经验
I have,I confess,precious little experience on the affairs of the heart,
但还能怎么解释呢?
but what other explanation could there possibly be?
- 这会是场灾难 - 你可以相信我 小姐
- This could be a disaster. - You can trust me,Mademoiselle.
你们又重新聚到一起我真高兴
It warms my heart to see you all together again.
露西会来吗?
Is Lucy joining us?
您真好 斯普里格斯夫人
This is very good of you,mrs. Spriggs.
我的荣幸 先生
My pleasure,sir.
真的
It is,really.
我真为你骄傲 亲爱的
I'm very proud of you,my dear.
我希望有人能告诉我这一切有什么意义
I wish someone would tell us the point of all this.
请原谅
If you will excuse me...
迪蒂斯汉姆夫人 我很高兴您能来
Lady Dittisham,I am delighted that you could make it.
我希望这趟能值得
I hope it's worth it.
天哪 这个地方要垮了!
God,this place is falling apart!
在我们进去之前...
Before we join the others...
我很想来杯马蒂尼
I'd kill for a Martini.
我们能谈谈吗?
... we might have a little word?
你不会放弃的 是吧?
You don't let up,do you?
开门见山吧...
To come straight to the point...
洗耳恭听
I'm pleased to hear it.
审讯之后
After the trial,
梅雷迪斯・布莱克有没有向你表示好感?
did Meredith Blake show any interest in you at all?
畜生! 愚蠢没脑子的畜生!
Animals! Stupid unthinking animals!
对你是多么可怕的折磨啊 亲爱的!
What a terrible ordeal for you,my dear!
你真是个勇敢的女孩! 埃尔莎
What a brave girl you are! Elsa,
自从见面后我一直对你有感觉 你知道吗?
I've had special feelings for you ever since we met,you know?
现在你孤零零的一个人...
And now you're all alone in the world...
别说了!
Do shut up!
- 你不吃惊吗? - 只是有点恶心
- Weren't you surprised? - Just vaguely nauseated.
现在我能来一杯马蒂尼吗?
Can I have my Martini now?
当然可以
But of course.
嗯... 真有趣!
Well... what a hoot!
就不能让我清净会吗?
Can't one have a moment's peace?
在伦敦的谈话中
You were not entirely honest with me
你对我并不坦诚
when we had that little chat in London.
- 是吗? - 是的 布莱克先生
- Is that so? - Yes indeed,Monsieur Blake.
在那个夏天 至少有一天晚上
On at least one night,during that Summer,
有人看到克雷尔夫人从你房间里出来
Madame Crale was seen coming out of your room
是谁告诉你的?
Who told you that?
这不关你的事
It's none of your damn business.
恐怕这关我的事 先生
I am affraid that it is,Monsieur,
如果你不把这事说清楚的话
if this matter is to be laid to rest.
她想她也许能试一试
She thought she might try it on.
他要离开我 我知道 我受不了没有他
He's going to leave me,I know he is. I can't bare the thought of being without him.
菲利浦 菲利浦
Philip,Philip...
有些时候我孤独得要疯掉
Sometimes I get so lonely I feel I'm going mad.
她总是觉得她想要什么就有什么
She always thought she could get what she wanted,
但我不吃那一套
but that didn't wash with me.
我觉得你该回去睡觉了
I think you better go back to bed.
当我说我不喜欢她 我没有撒谎
So,you see,when I said I didn't like her,I wasn't telling fibs.
确实
Non.
谢谢 先生
Merci,Monsieur.
事实上...
Actually...
也不全是事实
It's not quite true.
布莱克先生 你还好吧?
Monsieur Blake,are you all right?
一切都是一团糟!
Everything was such a mess!
从我们孩提时候就是这样
Always has been,ever since we were children.
她总是说些俏皮话
She was always ready with some sly remark.
艾米亚斯和我...
Amyas and I...
...我们...
... we...
...我们是真正的朋友
... we were true friends.
她受不了
She couldn't stand it.
他对我来说就是一切
He meant everything to me.
一切!
Everything!
我觉得梅雷迪斯知道
Meredith knew,I think.
凯若琳怀疑过
Caroline suspected.
但她说什么已经改变不了什么了
But nothing she could say changed anything.
是艾米亚斯 对吗? 一直都是
It's Amyas,isn't it? Still Amyas.
你就是忘不了他
You just can't get him out of your head.
你知道这有多可悲吗?
Do you have any idea how pathetic you are?
这只会让我更恨她
It just made me hate her all the more.
我...
I...
...我相信你会保守秘密
... I trust you keep this to yourself.
当然
Of course.
反正我也不在乎了
Not that I care much,anyway.
你们能来真是太好了
How kind of you to come.
你能开始了吗?
Do you think you can get on with the business in hand?
确实 先生 我正有此打算
Indeed,Monsieur,I was about to suggest the very same.
那么? 从哪开始呢?
Et alors,where to begin,hmm?
你们知道
As you know,
我来是为了解开艾米亚斯・克雷尔的死因
it was my purpose to dicover the truth about the murder of Amyas Crale.
我们都知道死因!
We all know the truth!
是的 确实如此 布莱克先生
Yes,indeed,Monsieur Blake,
但有时候 我们接受的事实
but sometimes,what we accept as the truth
只是管中窥豹 不是吗?
may not be the full story,n'est-ce pas?
有的时候 根本不是事实
And,sometimes,it may not be true at all.
好的 以下就是我了解到的:
D'accord. This is what I learned:
凯若琳・克雷尔从未维护自己的清白
that,at no time did Caroline Crale protest her innocence,
除了在给自己女儿的信中
except in a letter to her daughter;
在受审过程中 她也毫无畏惧
that,in the Dock,she showed no fear;
在给她妹妹的信中 她也接受了自己的命运
that,in a letter to her sister,she expressed acquiescence to her fate;
所有人都认为...
and that,in the opinion of everyone...
对不起 一个重要的人除外
Pardon,with one exception,most notable,
凯若琳・克雷尔是有罪的 - 她当然有罪!
Caroline Crale was guilty. - Of course she was!
但我不会接受别人的结论
But it was not for me to accept the verdict of others.
所以 重新检验一下事实是有必要的
Non,it was necessary for me to examine the facts,
确保这个案子的心理
and to ensure that the psycology of this case
能与那个时候相符
accorded itself with them.
毫无疑问 不论是动机
There's no doubt whatever that she had ample motive
还是证据 都对她不利
and much of the evidence,it tells against her:
在她的房间里找到香水瓶
the scent bottle discovered in her room;
她也承认偷过毒药
the poison she admitted to steal;
她和丈夫的争吵 扬言要杀了他
the row with her husband,where she threatened to kill him.
在心理分析上 这些没有什么不对的
None of this seems incorrect,psychologically.
但是 我们得看看一些不太真实的事
But,then,we come to something that does not quite ring true.
在梅雷迪斯・布莱克发现毒药不见后
After Meredith Blake discovers the poison is missing,
他过来跟他哥哥讨论
he rows over here to discuss it with his brother.
在他们回来的路上
On their way up to the house,
听到凯若琳和他丈夫的争论
they overhear a discussion between Caroline and her husband
关于送安吉拉去上学的事
on the vexed subject of Angela being sent away to school.
这样做太无耻了 艾米亚斯!
It's shameful behavior,Amyas!
- 你对她太残忍了 - 我们午饭后再谈
- You're being so hard on her. - We'll discuss this after lunch.
- 我去帮她打包 - 这让我感到很奇怪
- I'll see to her packing. - That does strike me as odd.
他们刚刚大吵了一架 她威胁要杀了他
They just had a row most horrific in which she has threatened to kill him,
但一会之后 他们又在讨论些不重要的琐事
and then,a short time later,they are having an argument relatively trivial
克雷尔先生说他去帮安吉拉打包
in which Monsieur Crale says he will see to Angela's packing.
你们不觉得很奇怪吗?
Now,does that not strike you as strange?
他为什么要帮安吉拉打包?
Why should he do her packing?
在她姐姐 家庭教师 保姆都在的时候?
When there is her sister,or the governess,or the housekeeper?
我不了解克雷尔先生
I did not know Monsieur Crale,
但是 我也没法想象他会叠裙子
But you know,somehow I can not picture him folding neatly
叠衬衫或是内衣
the skirts,the blouses,or the underwear.
另一件让我觉得奇怪的事是:
Another thing that striked as odd:
威胁要杀他之后
having just threatened to kill him,
凯若琳・克雷尔提出给她丈夫拿冰啤酒
Caroline Crale offers to bring to her husband a cold beer.
- 那是伪装 - 你这么觉得?
- Dissimulation. - You think so?
但是如果她想毒死他 为什么不选择...
But if she intends to poison him,wouldn't it be more intelligent to...
那是怎么说的?
What is the word?
在水上花园的那瓶啤酒里注射毒药呢
"Spike" the supply of beer that he has on the water garden,
那时候旁边没人 对吧?
when no-one was about,hmm?
凯若琳・克雷尔从家中给丈夫拿来了啤酒
Alors, Caroline Crale brings to him a beer from the house,
他喝下去了 他说
he drinks it,he says,
"今天的东西怎么都这么难喝"
"Everything tastes foul today",
午饭后她就发现他死了
and after lunch she finds him dead.
- 我们都知道 - 是啊是啊
- We know all this. - Oui,oui,bien sr.
现在 我告诉你们一些你们不知道的
But now,I offer some information which is new.
在威廉斯小姐请梅雷迪斯・布莱克叫医生之后
After asking Meredith Blake to call for a doctor,
她回到了水上花园
Mademoiselle Williams returns to the water garden.
你真的看见她做那些了吗?
You actually saw her do that?
这下都弄清了
Well,that settles it.
还没
Not necessarilly.
- 我的确看到了 - 那只是你的一面之辞
- That is what I saw. - And only your word for it.
我可不喜欢别人质疑我的话
I'm not accustomed to having my word doubted.
我没有质疑 威廉斯小姐
And I do not doubt it,Mademoiselle Williams.
我相信你的确看到了
I believe that what you saw took place exactly as you say that it did,
就因为你所看到的
and,because of what you saw,
我知道凯若琳・克雷尔是无辜的
I know that Caroline Crale was not guilty.
- 你该死的怎么知道的? - 冷静点
- Well,how the hell did you work that out? - Do calm down.
我可以告诉你
I will tell to you.
威廉斯小姐看见凯若琳・克雷尔
Mademoiselle Williams saw Caroline Crale
擦去啤酒瓶上的指纹
wipe off the fingerprints from the beer bottle
并且把她丈夫的指纹按到酒瓶上 注意
and impose the prints of her husband onto it... Onto the bottle,mark.
但是那毒参在杯子里 不在瓶子里
But the conium was in the glass,not the bottle.
警方并没有在瓶子上找到毒素
The police found no traces of it in the bottle.
瓶子里根本就没有毒参
No conium had ever been in the bottle.
凯若琳・克雷尔却不知道
And Caroline Crale,she did not know that .
如果是她下的毒
She,who has poisoned her husband,
她怎么会不知道毒下在哪里呢?
did not know how he had been poisoned?
那为什么要装成是自杀呢?
So,why make it look like suicide?
因为她知道谁是凶手
Because she knew who was the culprit
并且她愿意为那个人赴汤蹈火
and she would do anythining rather rather then let that person be suspected.
那么究竟是谁呢?
So,who could it be?
只有一个人
There was only one person
她会不惜一切保护她
whom she would be willing to protect at all costs.
沃伦小姐 我想读读你姐姐给你写的信
Mademoiselle Warren,I would like to read the letter your sister wrote you.
不!
No!
但是 小姐...
But,Mademoiselle...
我知道你什么意思
I realize what you are suggesting
但我拒绝 那封信是给我的
and I deny it utterly. That letter was meant for my eyes only.
- 安吉拉阿姨 求你了... - 不!
- Aunt Angela,please... - No!
为了我妈妈
For my mother's sake.
求你了
Please.
谢谢你 小姐
Merci,Mademoiselle.
"我亲爱的安吉拉
"My darling Angela,
我想让你知道一切都很好
"I want you to know that it is al alright.
我从未向你撒谎
"I have never lied to you,
我说我现在很开心 这也是真的
and I don't now when I say that I am happy,
我感到的是前所未有的宁静
that I feel a peace that I've never known before."
不要想了 不要为我难过
Don't look back,and don't grieve for me.
好好过你的生活 享受人生
Live your life and succeed.
一切都很好 亲爱的 都很好
It's all alright,my darling,it's all alright.
我要去陪艾米亚斯了 我很开心
I'm going to Amyas and I'm happy,
你也一定要快乐 欠的债总是要还的
and you must be too. One has to pay one's debts.
爱你的姐姐 凯若琳"
"Your loving sister,Caroline."
写得很好 不是么?
It is a beautiful letter,non?
令人惊奇的是 这里面少说了很重要的一点
And also quite remakable,for it contains one omission that is most tracking.
她并没有说她是无辜的
There is no protestation of innocence.
- 因为根本就没必要 - 是的
- Because it was unnecessary. - Oui,bien sr.
因为她认为她妹妹知道她无辜
Because she thought her sister knew that she was innocent
这是最可能的原因! 她唯一关心的
for the best of possible reasons! And her only concern
是宽慰你 劝你不要去自首
was to comfort,to reassure,and to advert of you having to confess.
"一切都很好 亲爱的
"It's all alright,my darling,
一切都很好"
it's all alright."
她想要我开心点 就这么简单
She wanted me to be happy,it's as simple as that.
是啊 这样你就不会太自责
Yes indeed,and so that the burden of your guilt may not be too great,
她告诉你"欠的债总是要还的"
she tells to you,"One must pay one's debts" .
现在她终于有机会偿还她欠你的债了
And now,she has,at last,the chance to repay you the debt she has to you
就是那些年来你因为眼睛所受的折磨
for the injury she caused you all those years before.
审讯 判决 啊! 没什么能够动摇她的心
And now the trial,the sentence,pff! Nothing can touch her,
因为 她终于觉得如释重负了
because,finally,she felt redeemed.
她获得了平静
She felt at peace with herself.
因为这个
And in the light of this,
所有事都解释得通了
everything falls into place.
听着 小屁孩...
Now look here,girlie...
我真希望你死
I wish you were dead.
当安吉拉把镇纸砸向艾米亚斯・克雷尔时
When Angela threw the paperweight at Amyas Crale,
她那段最深刻的记忆仿佛重现
the memory that haunts her is brought to life most vividly.
第二天早上 她看见安吉拉调了啤酒
Then,in the next morning,she sees Angela tempering with the beer...
你不介意的话 就给我拿着
I'll take it,if you don't mind.
...她把酒拿给了艾米亚斯 - 真难喝
... which she then brings to Amyas. - Tastes foul.
- 今天的东西怎么都这么难喝 - 午饭后
- Everything's foul today. - And after lunch,
她发现他死了
she finds him dead.
她确信他被下毒了
Alors, she is convinced he has been poisoned,
但是会是谁做的呢? 突然
but who could have done it? And then,suddenly,
她就想到了她
it its her.
安吉拉不想去学校 不接受埃尔莎
The resentment of Angela over the school,the desaproval of Elsa,
她昨天晚上又发那么大火
her rage on the night before,
早上又看见她调试啤酒
her tempering with the beer.
她也想起了
And she remembers also well
她自己在那个年纪的冲动
her own violent emotions at that age.
是的 安吉拉 肯定是她!
So yes,Angela. It has to be!
她马上想到的就是...
And the one thought that springs into her mind...
...怎么保护她
... is how to protect her.
所以 她擦去酒瓶上的指纹
So,she wipes the fingerprints from the bottle,
印上她丈夫的指纹 使之看起来像自杀
puts her husband's there to make it look like suicde,
尽快让安吉拉离开乡下
sends Angela out of the country as soon as possible,
只希望着
hoping,against hope,
她不要去自首
that she does not confess.
如果我真的做了的话 我肯定会去自首啊
But if I'd have done it,of course I'd have confessed.
我不会让凯若琳为我顶罪的
I'd never let Caroline suffer for what I'd done.
但是你的确在啤酒里做了手脚 不是吗?
But you did temper with the beer,did you not?
我不记得了!
I can't remember that!
布莱克先生 你说你在谋杀当天早上
Monsieur Blake,you said that you heard a noise in the laboratory
在实验室听到了奇怪的声音
in the morning of the murder.
是啊 可能是猫
Yes,just probably a cat.
也许不是 我会说 是有人爬进了窗子
Or probably not. I would suggest rather,it was someone who got in through
然后从架子上拿走了些东西
the sash window and took something from the shelf.
i草碱!
The valerian!
我准备放进艾米亚斯的饮料里的!
To put in Amyas' drink!
我记得我拿了
I remember taking it.
安吉拉!
Angela!
- 就是那天吗? - 是啊 小姐
- Was it really that day? - Oui,Mademoiselle.
- 那是i草碱 - 猫喜欢的那种?
- This is valerian. - The one that cats like?
它们爱死i草碱了
They can't get enough of it.
正是布莱克先生说的话给了你灵感
And it was the description given by Monsieur Blake which gave to you the idea.
是啊 我记得拿出了啤酒 然后凯若琳
Yes,I remeber getting out some beer and Caroline...
...在我把东西放进去之前就发现我了
... catching me before I could put the stuff in it.
我没想过这和那天的事情有关系
I never connected it with that particular day.
她以为是我!
She thought it was me!
噢! 我没有杀他
Oh! I didn't kill him.
- 我没有杀他 - 当然没有 亲爱的
- I didn't kill him. - Of course not,my dear.
你看不出她在说实话吗?
Can't you see she's telling the truth?
我看得出 因为我知道是谁杀了他
I see it quite clearly,because I know very well who killed him.
你不觉得你废话太多了吗 老家伙?
Don't you think you're milking it a bit,old man?
又是那种老掉牙的故事了
It is the older story in the world:
两个女人和一个男人
two women and one man.
我们以为 按照常理
What we have taken for granted is that
那个男人肯定会离开他的妻子
the man would leave his wife
投入另一个女人的怀抱
for the other woman.
我却认为他根本就不想
But I would like to suggest here now is that he had no intention of doing
那样做
anything of that kind.
毕竟 他曾经爱过的那些女人
After all,the women he had fallen in love with in the past
从不向他奢求什么 但是这次不同
never expected too much from him,but this time it was different.
她只是个女孩罢了
She was just a girl,
这女孩爱憎分明
who saw the world in black and white.
她对他一片真心
She had the passion for him,
并且天真地以为他也是一样
and so assumed he had for her.
她以为他会理所应当地
She assumed,without question,it was for life,
离开他的妻子
so,naturally,he would leave his wife.
- 他说过他会 - 也许只是善意的谎言
- He said he would. - Well,a little white lie,perhaps.
他只不过想画完画而已
All he really wanted was to finish the painting,
没什么能够阻挡他 当埃尔莎・格里尔
and nothing could be allowed to stand in the way. And when Elsa Greer
把他们之间的秘密约定说出来时 他很生气
let the cat from the bag,he was furious,
但他没有马上警觉
but he was not concerned unduly.
毕竟 凯若琳只需要再忍耐几天就好了
After all,Caroline had only to put up with things for a few days longer,
到时候他就会说出真相
then he would tell her the truth,
她会相信他 像以前一样
and she would believe him,as so often before.
埃尔莎・格里尔呢? 她很快会忘了这件事
And Elsa Greer? She would get over it soon enough.
就在那天的前一晚 我觉得他应该是有些担忧
But by that last evening,I believe that he was getting worried
他以为凯若琳・克雷尔会像以前一样把这当真
that Caroline Crale was taking things more seriously than usual.
第二天一早 他决定说清楚
And,by the following morning,I think he had decided to come clean.
你是我生命中唯一的女人 凯若琳
You're the only woman in my life,Carol.
你一直都是 以后也会是 你知道的
You always were,you always will be,. You know that.
她对我什么都不是 不是
She is nothing to me. Nothing.
她的确曾经让我怦然心动 但是现在已经没了
She was,yes. She knocked me for six to start with,but now is gone.
都结束了 我向上帝发誓 她只是个孩子
It's over. I swear to God. She's just a kid.
只是一时情迷 就是这样
A passing fancy,that's all.
你和你的女人!
You and your women!
总有一天我要杀死你 艾米亚斯
Someday I'll kill you,Amyas.
- 别傻了 - 我发誓我一定会!
- Don't be an idiot. - I swear to God I will!
他不知道的是
What he did not know
埃尔莎・格里尔在窗外听得清清楚楚
was that Elsa Greer had overheard every word.
她告诉我的并不是真的
And the account that she gave to me of the conversation was not the true one.
你对自己很有信心 不是么 波罗先生?
You're very sure of yourself,aren't you,Monsieur Poirot?
对于这件事 迪蒂斯汉姆夫人
Of this,Lady Dittisham,
我的确很有信心
yes,I am.
当艾米亚斯・克雷尔出了房间
When Amyas Crale came down
说他想继续画画
and said he wanted to get on,
你说你要去换衣服
you said you had to go and change.
你最后确实...换了衣服
Which you did... eventually.
你知不知道
I wonder you'd realized
克雷尔女士知道她丈夫对你的态度时
how angry was Madame Crale with her husband
她有多么生气? - 真感人啊
for his treatment of you? - How very touching.
当菲利浦・布莱克看见她从书房走出时
When Philip Blake encountered her coming out of the library...
- 早上好 - 太残忍了 太残忍了
- Good morning. - It's too cruel,too cruel.
她其实想的是你
... it was of you she was thinking.
我想知道如果她知道 那时候
I wonder what she would have thought had she known that,
你在她的房间 预谋杀死她的丈夫
at that very moment,
还准备栽赃在她身上
you were in her room preparing to murder her husband
她会怎么想?
and put the blame on her?
我对其他事情也很有信心 迪蒂斯汉姆小姐
You see,something else that I am sure of,Lady Dittisham,
谋杀前一天下午 在实验室里
is that in the laboratory,in the previous afternoon,
你肯定看见了凯若琳・克雷尔偷那瓶毒药
you would have seen Caroline Crale steel the poison.
布莱克先生在和你谈话时背对着实验室
Monsieur Blake had his back to the room when he was talking to you,
所以 你很有可能看见她
so,it was perfectly possible for you to see her,
也只有你有可能看见
the only person who could do so.
抱歉啊 梅雷迪斯 这收藏太有趣啦
Sorry,Merri. It's such a fascinating colection...
当你拿到毒药后 你就去了花园找艾米亚斯
And once you had the poison,you went to join Amyas in the garden,
给他倒了点啤酒
poured him some beer...
敬我的蒙娜丽莎
To my Mona Lisa.
和平常一样 他仰头就喝下去了
... and he tossed it back,in his usual manner.
我亲爱的艾米亚斯
My darling Amyas.
他一边画着 你就在一边看着
As he painted,you watched and watched,
看毒药究竟什么时候生效 过不了多久
waiting for the poison to take its efect. A short time later,
你去拿围巾 这时凯若琳・克雷尔又来...
you went to fetch a shawl and Caroline Crale again took the opportunity...
代表你劝她的丈夫
... to confront her husband on your behalf.
你的行为太可耻了 艾米亚斯!
It's shameful,your behavior,Amyas!
你对她太残忍了
You're being too hard on her.
老天啊! 都解决了 我去帮她打包
For God's sake! It's all settled. I'll send her packing.
就在这时从码头回来的布莱克兄弟
And it was this that the Blake brothers misheard,
听到了他们的谈话
on their way up from the jetty.
这样的对话的确很容易让人误解 不是么?
An error that is understandable,n'est-ce pas?
然后 你 拿着围巾回来了
You,then,returned with a shawl,
然后凯若琳・克雷尔 落入了你的圈套
and then Caroline Crale,she plates straight into your hands,
因为她刚刚给了她丈夫一杯冰啤酒
for she brought to her husband a bottle of cold beer.
真难喝! 今天的东西怎么都这么难喝
It tastes foul! Everything tastes foul today.
"今天的东西怎么都这么难喝"
"Everything tastes foul today",
这表明在凯若琳・克雷尔给他那杯啤酒之前
which suggests that he had tasted something else unpleasant
他还喝了其它难喝的东西
before the beer that Caroline Crale had brought to him.
接着 你坐下来 摆好姿势
And so,you sat,and posed,
和他聊天 还向梅雷迪斯・布莱克挥手
and chatted,and waved to Meredith Blake.
你真是个好演员啊!
You played your part beautifully!
该死的风湿!
Bloody rheumatism!
...艾米亚斯・克雷尔一直画
... while Amyas Crale painted on,and on,
直到他的腿麻木
until his limbs failed,
讲话开始变得艰难 他横躺在长椅上
and his speech thickened,and he layed sprawled on the bench,
很无助 但是他的意识还是清醒的!
helpless,with his mind still clear!
当梅雷迪斯・布莱克
And when Meredith Blake appeared
从那条黑暗的小路进入明亮的花园时
from the shadowy path onto the sunny garden,
他的眼睛还看不清楚
he could not see clearly.
只看到他的老友缓慢地转过身来
Only his friend turning slowly around,
却无法告诉他
unable to covey the fact that
他现在已经几近瘫痪 并且快死了
he was in the grip of a paralysis that was fatal.
在回去的路上 你踩碎了那支滴管
En route to the house,you crushed the pipet on the foot,
也就是警察找到的线索
the traces of which the police were to find.
接着你去吃午饭
And then went to lunch,
让艾米亚斯・克雷尔就这样死去
leaving Amyas Crale to his fate.
谢谢你 波罗先生
Thank you,Monsieur Poirot.
小姐
Mademoiselle.
艾米亚斯死了
Amyas dead,
凯若琳被绞死
Caroline hanged...
这么多年来...
After all these years...
这么多年来!
After all these years!
你很聪明啊 不是么?
You're very clever,aren't you?
你不会想要我去自首吧
I hope you don't expect me to confess.
那么 你打算怎么做?
So,what are you going to do?
我会尽我所能去引导有关部门
I shall do what I can to induce the appropriate authorities
还死去的凯若琳・克雷尔一个清白
to grant to Caroline Crale a postumous free pardon.
那我呢? 你会把我怎么样?
And me? What're you going to do about me?
我会在必要人员面前作出结论
I shall lay my conclusions before the necessary people.
如果他们决定起诉你 他们可以那么做
If they decide there is a case against you,they may act.
但是 我觉得...
But,it is my opinion...
...证据还是不足
... that the evidence is not suficient.
只有推理 证据不够
Inferences only,not facts.
而且 我觉得他们不会急切地想要起诉...
Moreover,I believe they won't be anxious to proceed against a...
...你这样身份的人
... person in your position.
当我看到凯若琳偷毒药的时候
When I saw Caroline take the conium,
我以为她想自杀
I thought she meant to kill herself.
但是第二天早上
But in the next morning,
当我偷听到他们谈论我 我...
when I overheard them talking about me,I...
我爱他...
I loved him...
...但他却把我丢在一旁
... and he was just stringing me along.
她为我感到内疚
And she felt sorry for me.
我看着他死的 波罗先生
I watched him die,Monsieur Poirot.
我觉得那时候的我才是活着的
And I never felt more alive,
但我不知道我也杀死了自己
but what I didn't understand was that I was killing myself.
感觉上不是他们死了
It was as if they hadn't died at all,
而是我死了
but I had.
我死了 波罗先生
I died,Monsieur Poirot.
埃尔莎!
Elsa!
开枪啊 露西
Come on then,Lucy.
开枪打我啊 你很想的
Shoot me. You know you want to.
别听她的 小姐
Do not listen to her,Mademoiselle.
这就对了
That's right.
只需扣下扳机
Just pull the trigger.
如果你听她的 她就得逞了
If you do,she will have won.
来啊 开枪啊
Come on,do it.
你不是在害怕 对吧?
You're not affraid,are you?
如果你杀了她 你是在自掘坟墓
If you kill her,you kill yourself.
轻轻一摁 只需这样做
Just one little squeeze,that's all it takes.
放过她 小姐 正义会得到伸张的
Spare her,Mademoiselle,and justice may still be done.
露西 开枪啊!
Lucy,shoot me!